Finding Aid for the Los Angeles Unified School District Board of Education Records LSC.1923
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Subject Files, 1913-2012
  - Race Question, 1934-1987 (Box 1593, Box 1594, Box 1595, Box 1596, Box 1597, Box 1598, Box 1599, Box 1600, Box 1601, Box 1602, Box 1603, Box 1604, Box 1605, Box 1606, Box 1607, Box 1608, Box 1609, Box 1610, Box 1611, Box 1612, Box 1613, Box 1614, Box 1615, Box 1616, Box 1617, Box 1618, Box 1619, 
    Box 1597-1598: Board policies and procedures regarding tolerance, racial discrimination, segregation and not recording the race of pupils, Supreme Court of the United States Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka opinion, Resolution on Inter-Racial Democracy in the Schools, Report of California Supreme Court Case of Arthur Wysinger by his Guardian, Edmund Wysinger, Appellant v. S.A. Crookshank, Respondent, correspondence protesting the boundary changes between Jordan and South Gate High Schools, Minutes concerning police presence and lockdown at Jordan High School, Inter-office correspondence report on CORE sit-in demonstration, County Counsel's opinion on de facto school segregation (1934-1965).
    Box 1599-1601: Personnel and Schools Committee Report on the emergency closing of schools during the Watts Riots, press releases on the results of two racial and ethnic surveys of the LA City Schools mandated by the State Board of Education, Watts Teachers Pilot Project Report, correspondence and petitions opposing bussing children out of neighborhood schools, correspondence from Superintendent Crowther regarding the distribution of pupils by race, propaganda from the National Congress of Parents and Teachers AGAINST Bussing, First Informative Report on District Integration Policy, "The Dynamics of a Black Caucus" by Homer A. Jack, Administrator's In Depth Seminars in Problems of Desegregation as They Relate to Large City Schools (1965-1968).
    Box 1602-1605: Voluntary Bussing Program Progress Report, Adult Education Committee Report on the establishment of the Adult Bilingual Experimental School, Press Releases on Minority Enrollment and Ethnic Studies, Los Angeles Goals Council Report ont Goals for Ghettos and Barrios, Mexican American Education Commission programs and recommendations, list of racially imbalanced schools, correspondence and motions concerning the Crawford case, recommendations for the Community Ad Hoc Committee on Integration, Educational Development Committee Report on the East L.A. Dropout Prevention Project (1968-1977).
    Box 1606-1608: Addenda to Progress Report on Development of Planning Efforts for Staff Integration, Personnel and Schools Committee Report adopting Equal Opportunity Policy and Affirmative Action Policy for District Personnel, Progress Report on Plans to Balance Certificated Staff, list of organizations and groups represented on the Citizens' Advisory Committee on School Integration, Mexican Culture and Heritage Teacher Guide, Staff Integration Proposal, Reverend Jesse L. Jackson's press statement on PUSH/WEST Los Angeles and integration in the Los Angeles public schools, Committee of the Whole Communication on the Superintendent's Staff Unit for Integration, Dr. Ernest H. Smith and Dr. Ernie A. Smith's Board presentation statements entitled Pupil Teacher Integration - Is There a Hidden Agenda? and A Case for Bilingual and Bicultural Education for United States Slave Descendents of African Origin (1974-1976).
    Box 1609-1614: Citizens' Advisory Committee On Student Integration (CASCI) Reports and Board responses, correspondence and petitions against mandatory bussing, student letters for and against bussing, Racial and Ethnic Survey, Staff Response to Guidelines and Directions for the Development of an Integration Plan, School Observer newsletters with special integration reports, Court Reports on the Crawford integration hearings, city map showing businesses and building looted, damaged and/or burned and destroyed and deaths during the Watts Riot, Fiscal Summary of McCone Commission Recommendations (1965-1977).
    Box 1615: School Segregation on Our Doorstep: The Los Angeles Story by John and Laree Caughey, Segregation Blights Our Schools by John W. Caughey, Violence in the City -- An End or a Beginning?: A Report by the Governor's Commission on the Los Angeles Riots (McCone Commission), Summary Report of the National Advisory Commission on Civil Disorders, U.S. Riot Commission Report: What Happened? Why Did It Happen? What Can Be Done?, Schools Are For Going To/Las Escuelas Son Para Ir A booklets, The Negro Family: The Case for National Action, Headway: A Report by the Economic and Youth Opportunities Agency of Greater Los Angeles, Community Profiles and Orientation to Central Los Angeles, East Los Angeles: Nuestra Comunidad, Orientation to South Los Angeles Communities: Florence, Green Meadows, Watts, The View From Watts: A Series of Articles Reprinted from the Los Angeles Times, de facto segregation newspaper clippings (1964-1977).
    Box 1616-1617: Approach to a Human Relations Program for Junior and Senior High Schools, copies of Rumford Act AB 1963 statements to the Board, Office of Urban Affairs, Urban News newsletters, status memoranda regarding Crawford v. Board of Education, Petitions from residents of the Watts District to end all forms of segregation in schools, specifically in the Jordan and South Gate High School Districts, Crawford v. Board of Education Summons and Complaint, Model Cities Evaluation Report and curricular materials (1963-1977).
    Box 1618-1621: Citizens Compensatory Education Advisory Committee Minutes, Compensatory Education Reports (1964-1987).
  - Radiation, 2000 June 27-2006 June 29 (Box 1622, Folder 1)
    Copy of a motion concerning the effects of non-ionizing radiation and Board Report regarding the approval of an agreement with the Los Angeles Police Department to install a wireless antenna on the roof of Jordan High School in conjunction with the Jordan Downs Public Safety Initiative.
  - Radio, 1938-2008 (Box 1622, Folder 2-10)
    Materials include California State FM Radio System Plan, contracts, Radio Committee Reports, correspondence concerning programs, texts of broadcasts and communications on two-way radio systems in busses.
  - Rainy Day, 1944 November 15-1960 January 7 (Box 1623, Folder 1)
    Bulletins on emergency and inclement weather procedures.
  - Rapid Learners, 1955-1975 (Box 1623, Folder 2-4, Box 1684, Box 1685)
    Committee Reports and Communications, materials presented to the Board and Progress Reports concerning Rapid Learners and the Gifted Program.
  - Reading Plan, 1999-2003 (Box 1623, Folder 5)
    Reports, Policies and Evaluations of the District Reading Plan and Reading First Initiative.
  - Recreation, 1946 February 11-2000 February 16 (Box 1722, Folder 3-4, Box 1624, Folder unknown container, Box 1625, Box 2076, Box 2077)
    Reports and Communications regarding recreation services provided by the District, policies for the use of school facilities for recreation, use of busses for recreation program, camping program, Recreation and Youth Services Planning Council, Metropolitan Recreation and Youth Services Council and Bell Community Recreation Program.
    Materials also include Recreation Policies and Practices of the Youth Services Division, In the Next Ten Years... Factors Influencing Recreation in Los Angeles County, Manual on Use of School Facilities, Leisure Time Activities for Girls in Los Angeles County, Get High On Life: In-Service Training Manual, Our Schools and Recreation: The Youth Services Program of the Los Angeles City Schools, A Comparative Analysis of the Guiding Principles of the Youth Services Program of the Los Angeles City Schools with the Principles Emerging from Recent Recreation Literature and School-City Cooperation and Coordination of Recreation and Youth Services in Los Angeles.
  - Receiving Schools Project, 1982 September 30 (Box 1626, Folder 1)
    Educational Development Committee proposal to meet the needs of non-resident students involved in Receiving Schools Project.
  - Recruitment, 1981 March 2-1986 November 3 (Box 1626, Folder 2)
    Personnel and Schools Committee Communications concerning payment of expenses for teacher-recruiters.
  - Recycling, 1980 June 2-1995 January 3 (Box 1626, Folder 3)
    Committee Reports and Communications regarding the District's recycling program.
  - Red Cross, 1936-1971 (Box 1626, Folder 4-7)
    Reports and correspondence regarding Red Cross annual drives, contributions and subscriptions to the "Red Cross News."
  - Redistricting, 1983 January 10-2002 February 13 (Box 1627, Folder 1-2)
    Redistricting proposals created by the LA Redistricting Commission for the LAUSD public hearings and City Council action.
  - Reduction In Force, 2002 March 12-2008 June 10 (Box 1627, Folder 3)
    Board of Education Reports authorizing the Human Resources Division to send Reduction-In-Force notices to employees.
  - Refugees, 1980 June 23-1990 November 19 (Box 1627, Folder 4)
    Committee Reports and Communications concerning assistance for refugee students.
  - Regional Occupational Centers and Programs, 1978-2008 (Box 1627, Folder 5-7)
    Reports and Communications regarding Regional Occupational Centers and programs such as Work-Study, designed to support career technical education.
  - Reimbursement, 1981 June 1-2001 February 13 (Box 1628, Folder 1-3)
    Committee Reports concerning agreements for reimbursements.
  - Reinstatement, 1991 September 3-2000 November 28 (Box 1628, Folder 4)
    Board of Education Reports regarding student reinstatements after periods of expulsion.
  - Religious Education, 1942-2003 (Box 1629, Folder 1-3, Box 1628, Folder 5-6)
    Correspondence concerning religious instruction, prayer in school and bulletins on released-time classes in religious or moral instruction.
  - Relocation Assistance, 1990-2007 (Box 1630, Folder 1-3, Box 1629, Folder 4-5)
    Relocation Assistance Program informational brochures to assist residents with the relocation process in the event the District decides to purchase their property for school construction projects, Relocation Plans and guidelines.
  - Repair and General Maintenance Fund, 1988-1989 (Box 1630, Folder 4)
    Committee Reports regarding the District's Repair and General Maintenance Fund.
  - Report Cards, 1952-1993 (Box 1630, Folder 5-9)
    Samples of the District's report cards and progress reports for student assessment marks.
  - Reports, 1880-2008 (Box 2078, Folder 1-2, Box 1631, Box 1632, Box 1633, Box 1634, Box 1635, Box 1636, Box 1637, Box 1638, Box 1639, Box 1640, Box 1641, Box 1642, Box 1643, Box 1644, Box 1645, Box 1646, Box 1647, Box 1648, Box 1649, Box 1650, Box 1651, Box 1652, Box 1653, Box 1654, Box 1655, Box 1656, Box 1657, Box 1658, Box 1659, Box 1660, Box 1661, Box 1662, Box 1663, Box 1664, Box 1665, Box 1666, Box 1667)
    Materials include reports created by the District, the bulk of which are Controller's Financial Reports.
    On July 1, 1986, the Controller position named changed to Chief Business and Financial Officer.
    Box 1,631-1,647: Annual Reports of the Board to the Los Angeles County Superintendent of Schools, District Superintendent's Reports to the Board, memos and correspondence regarding distribution of the Board Reports and Minutes, Calendar of Reports, Expenditures Classified by Schools, Controller's Semiannual, Annual and Summary of Monthly Financial Reports (1929-1986).
    Box 1,648-1,654: Controller's Monthly Financial Reports, Summaries of Monthly Financial Reports, Semiannual Reports, Third Quarter Reports and Annual Reports, Chief Business and Financial Officer's Monthly Financial Reports, Summaries of Monthly Financial Reports, Semiannual Reports and Third Quarter Reports, District's Comprehensive Annual Financial Report (1978-1989).
    Box 1,655-1,660: Controller's Annual Report of Expenditures Classified by Schools, School Expenditures and Facilities Annual Report, Chief Business and Financial Officer's Monthly Financial Reports and Semiannual Reports, First, Second and Third Period Interim Financial Reports, Capsule Reports, Comprehensive Annual Financial Reports, Child Welfare and Attendance Reports, Health Education and Health Services Branch Annual Reports, Business Division Annual Reports (1945-1998).
    Box 1,661-1,663: Transiency and Stability in the LAUSD Evaluation Reports, Report of Plans of the 1986 Graduates, Language Development Program for African American Students: Implementation Evaluation, Survey of Instructional Programs, Integration Program Reports, Integration Evaluation Reports, Financial Implications of Andersen Recommendations, National Defense Training Report, Annual Reports of the Board of Education for 1880-1881, 1895-1896 and 1907-1908, Copy of Board of Education Annual Report for 1883-1884, District Annual Progress Reports and Superintendent's Annual Reports (1880-1995).
    Box 1,664-1,667: Comprehensive Annual Financial Reports, First, Second and Third Period Interim Financial Reports (1995-2008).
    Box 2,078: Weekly Reports of School Depredations (1946-1953).
  - Research, 1930 February 20-1987 June 29 (Box 1728)
    Materials include Superintendent Bruce A. Findlay's "Cooperative Procedures for Research Studies," an agreement with the Martin Luther King Legacy Association to conduct a home education and development program, an Informative Report from the Personnel Commission on Residence Requirements for Classified Employees and a series approved by the Committee on Research Studies including "Activities of General Elementary Supervisors in Cities of Over 200,000," "Objectives of Education for Gifted Children in California Elementary Schools" and "Public Marking Practices in Los Angeles City Senior High Schools."
  - Reserve Funds, 1986 November 3-1994 November 21 (Box 1729, Folder 1)
    Reports and Communications concerning the following Reserve Funds: Attendance Incentive, Undistributed - Economic Uncertainties, Undistributed - District Operations, Federal Emergency Management Agency, Special, Regular Program and Lottery.
  - Reserve Officers' Training Corps, 1935 July 18-2000 January 11 (Box 1729, Folder 2-8)
    The Junior Division of the Army Reserve Officers' Training Corps (R.O.T.C.) Program was established under the provisions of the National Defense Act of 1916 as a military training program to teach students practical skills in subjects such as map reading, military history, organization of the Army, use of small arms and rifle marksmanship.
    The Board authorized the Program's initial presence at the following high schools: Belmont, Fairfax, Franklin, Garfield, Hamilton, Hollywood, Lincoln, Los Angeles, Manual Arts, North Hollywood, Roosevelt, San Pedro, University, Van Nuys and expanded units at additional secondary school sites.
    Materials include Reports concerning inventories of U.S. Government issued equipment at high school sites with Reserve Officers' Training Corps (R.O.T.C.) programs, bills for stolen rifles and other lost government property, booklet on the Department of Army created curriculum and extra-curricular activities such as rifle range practice by student teams at school site rifle ranges, correspondence regarding incidents of illegal hazing and initiation carried out by student members of the Franklin High School ROTC unit and a statement of opposition to school funding for the ROTC by Esther Lewin of Women Strike for Peace.
  - Retention Patterns, 1983 December 12-1992 March 30 (Box 1730, Folder 1)
    Retention Patterns in the LAUSD Reports prepared by Program Evaluation and Assessment Branch staff that present retention rates broken down by sex, grade and ethnicity.
  - Retirement, 1936 November 30-2008 March 25 (Box 1730, Folder 2-10, Box 1731, Box 1732, Box 1733, Box 1734, Box 1735, Box 1736, Box 1737, Box 1738, Box 1739, Box 1740, Box 1741, Box 1742, Box 1743, Box 1744, Box 1745, Box 1746, Box 1747, Box 1748, Box 1749, Box 1750, Box 1751, Box 1752, Box 1753, Box 1754, Box 1755)
    The Los Angeles City School District Retirement System, the Los Angeles City High School District Retirement System and the Los Angeles City Junior College District Retirement System were established as of September 1, 1937.
    Materials include District Retirement Election Plans, Procedures, Rules, Regulations, Proposals and Retirement Board Meeting Minutes as well as records pertaining to the State Employees' Retirement System.
    Box 1,730-1,733: District Retirement Election Plans, Elementary and High School Retirement Board Consolidation Meeting Minutes, Retirement Handbook of Information, State Employees' Retirement System, Retired Certificated Transfers to State System, Teacher Union Retirement Proposals, Retirement Board Election Procedures, Certificated Retirement Elections (1937-1972).
    Box 1,734-1,737: Investment Counsel, Interest Rates, Legal Opinions, Medical Board Personnel, Membership, State Employees' Retirement System Payments, District Retirement Board Oath of Office, Termination of Employee Service, List of Retiring Employees, Congratulations on Promotions, Actuarial Services, Conventions (1937-1973).
    Box 1,738-1,740: Budget, Annual Reports, "District Retirement Act, Other Pertinent Legal Extracts, Rules and Regulations," Retirement Rules, Disability Rules, Retirement Age Limit, Insurance Plan Deductions, Legislation, Recommendation Report of Mortality and Service Tables for Adoption and Rates of Contribution for Certification by the Board, Contributions, District Retirement Discontinuance (1937-1972).
    Box 1,741-1,743: LAUSD and Los Angeles City Junior College District Retirement System Meeting Minutes, Unified District Retirement Board Minutes (1962-1972).
    Box 1,744-1,751: District Retirement Board Election results, Lists of Eligible Voters, Tally Sheets and State Employees' Retirement System Survivor Benefits Election materials and lists of employees, Dissolution or Disposition of District Retirement System Election, Earned Salary Allowance Poll (1945-1966).
    Box 1,752-1,755: Retirement System History, District Sponsored Hospital-Medical Program History, Benefits, Retirement Age Limit, Health and Welfare Coverage for Retired Board Members, Classified Retirement System and Election, Social Security, State Teachers Retirement System (STRS) for Certificated Personnel, STRS Bulletin, California Public Employees Retirement System (PERS) Newsletters, Maxicare Health Plan, A Review of Domestic Partners Coverage, Investments (1936-2008).
  - Revolving Appropriations/Cash Account, 1992 September 21-1992 October 5 (Box 1756, Folder 1)
    Communication from the Superintendent concerning the establishment of revolving cash accounts.
  - Rewards, 1973-1999 (Box 1756, Folder 2)
    Standing Committee Reports, Board Resolutions and flyers offering rewards for information leading to the apprehension and conviction of persons who committed crimes of arson, vandalism, burglary, battery, assault with a deadly weapon, rape or homicide against students, employees, volunteers or school properties.
  - Rideshare Program, 1979-1995 (Box 1756, Folder 3)
    Reports and newsletters regarding the District's support and incentives for the employee Rideshare Program.
  - Royalties, 1953-1996 (Box 1756, Folder 4)
    District receipts of oil royalties received from properties and reports regarding royalties for the use of District created instructional materials.
  - Rules (Board), 1935-2004 (Box 1756, Folder 5-8, Box 1757, Box 1758, Box 1759, Box 1760, Box 1761, Box 1762, Box 1763, Box 1764, Box 1765)
    Materials relate to the Board's adoption and processing of Board Rules and include proposals, modifications, amendments and revisions to Board Rules and Administrative Regulations governing the Board and the District.
    Box 1,756-1,761: Rules (1935-1975).
    Box 1,762: Correspondence between the Board, UTLA and other employee organizations following the April 13, 1970 to May 13, 1970 teacher strike concerning the adoption, legality according to the Winton Act and dismissal of proposed Board Rule 3700 which sought to recognize UTLA as the sole bargaining unit for the District's teachers. Board Rule 3700 was 53 pages in length, affected every teacher's contract and was determined illegal by the courts. The Board voted to drop its appeal on November 1, 1971 (1970-1971).
    Box 1,763-1,764: Rules including a savings and costs review of proposed Board Rule 1971 which requires the District to make a contribution for each State Teachers' Retirement System (STRS) member who retires between ages 55 and 60 (1975-2004).
    Box 1,765: Board Rule 1276 - Circulation of Petitions, History of Rules and Regulations, Education Code Sections and State Board of Education Rules and Regulations for Secondary Schools (1938-1972).
  - Safes, 1948 January 28-1962 July 31 (Box 1766, Folder 1)
    Correspondence from Board Secretariat James R. Edwards concerning access to the vault, Communications on the installation of safes at secondary schools and Law and Rules Committee Communication authorizing the installation of combination tear gas protective system and relocking device for safes at the following schools: Venice, Theodore Roosevelt, Belmont and John Adams Junior High.
  - Safety, 1930-2006 (Box 1766, Folder 2-9, Box 1767, Box 1768, Box 1769)
    Correspondence, Reports and petitions concerning safety concerns on and near school sites, environmental safety hazards, campus security improvements, school crossings and safety rules.
    Materials also include Handbook of Safety Rules and Regulations From The Administrative Guide, Report on Safety Conditions at Baldwin Hills Elementary School which includes school site black and white photographs, Accident Control Survey and Analysis Report, Toward the Development of a Campus and Community Safety Indicator System: Understanding Students' Perception of Safety Report and Safe Drinking Water Program: Lead Level Determination Report.
  - Safety and Technology Program, 2002 December 10-2004 June 22 (Box 1770, Folder 1-2)
    Facilities Division authorization for the use of a design/build procurement contract for approximately 480 Safety and Technology projects and "Hazard Communication and Your Right-To-Know" binder prepared by the Environmental Health and Safety Branch.
  - Salvage, 1942-2003 (Box 1770, Folder 3-4)
    Bulletin regarding the Salvage for Victory Campaign in the Los Angeles City Schools, correspondence concerning Scrap Metal and Rubber Drives and Facilities Division Report on auctions for recycled and salvaged items.
  - Scholarships, 1935-1999 (Box 1970, Folder 6-8, Box 1771)
    Reports and Communications concerning scholarship funds and the manual, "Scholarships: A Guidance Tool for Scholarship Advisers."
  - Schools, 1933-2009 (Box 1772, Box 1773, Box 1774, Box 1775, Box 1776, Box 1777, Box 1778, Box 1779, Box 1780, Box 1781, Box 1782, Box 1783, Box 1784, Box 1785, Box 1786, Box 1787, Box 1788, Box 1789, Box 1790, Box 1791, Box 1792, Box 1793, Box 1794, Box 1795, Box 1796, Box 1797)
    Board of Education Reports and correspondence concerning school personnel, programs, legislation, proposals, calendars and programs.
    Box 1,772-1,774: Accelerated School, Accountability Act, Accreditation, Ad-Hoc Committee to Coordinate School Development Projects, Administrative Personnel, Adopt-A-School Program, Adult Education, Age Requirements, Alphabetical List, Alternative School, Assistance and Intervention, School-Based Administrator Compensation Study, School-Based Health Clinic, School-Based Pupil Motivation and Maintenance Program, School-Based Educational Technology Program (1956-2008).